The TSOE OMVS command will allow users to start more than one session with the shell.
Only one session is displayed at a time on the screen.
The multi-session support in the shell allows these shell processes to reside as tasks
in the same address space.
The user can switch between different sessions using a PF key.
The following are OMVS sub-commands to control the multi-session support.
Those are open, which starts a new shell session.
Close or quit, closes a shell session.
Quit all, ends all sessions and returns to TSOE.
Next sesh, switches to the next session and previous sesh, switches to the previous session.
The non-TSOE user can log into multiple shell sessions using the same user ID and password.
You can also be logged onto the shell using the TSOE interface and the R login interface
using the same user ID and password.
So here's an example of a shell script with some logic.
This example has a for loop, for do, done.
It also has an if condition that runs a sequence of commands if a particular condition is met.
If then fi.
This example of a shell script takes one positional parameter, giving the name of a file.
The script looks in the working directory and finds the names of all .c files.
The if control structure inside the for loop tests each file to see if it's older than
the file named on the command line.
If the .c file is older, echo displays the name and the file is compiled.
So what we've seen there is a shell script that has the capability to run a sequence
of commands stored in a text file.
The commands in the file can be run by entering the file name on the command line.
After a shell script is created, a user needs read and execute permission to run the script.
A shell is like a program made up of shell commands.
The shell supports many of the features of regular programming languages like variables,
control structures and functions.
A set of zosunix extensions to TSOE Rex provides the capability for Rex execs to access zosunix
callable services.
The zosunix extensions to Rex are called syscall commands and they have names that correspond
to the names of the callable services they invoke, for example exec, fork and pipe.
Rex execs using zosunix extensions can run from TSOE or in zosbatch and access the zosunix
functions and services through a host command environment rather than discrete external functions.
The host command environment is called syscall.
The environment must be initialized by a syscall's on statement in the beginning of the exec.
Rex execs can also be run in the zosunix shell or from a C program using the exec system
call.
This is different from shell scripts which are only interpreted in the shell.
This also means that shell scripts can invoke a Rex exec just like they would invoke any
program.
When running a Rex exec in the shell or from a C program, the syscall environment is
automatically initialized.
There are many ways in zosunix to send a message to another user.
Which method to use depends on the requirements and the timeframes you want the message to
be sent, such as logger and write.
As a TSO user, you might prefer to just use facilities provided by TSO instead.
The clock daemon cron is a facility that allows you to run a command at a specific time, run
a command in batch when the system activity is low, or set up commands, scripts or programs
to run at the same time every day or every week.
Batch work is assigned bottom priority.
The cron daemon examines the at, batch or crontab files at initialization or whenever
they change and start the functions at the specified times.
It uses the timezone in effect when the command is executed.
Therefore, be sure to set the TZ environment variable before starting cron.
In the next video, we'll look at BPX batch.